We all know by now that Jeff Hafley will
lead the Miami Dolphins into this new
era, but it can be easy to forget what
may have earned him this opportunity in
the first place. At the end of the day,
Halfley is a guy who loves coaching
football, and he has become an elite
schemer of defense, no matter the
situation or personnel. And for Dolphins
fans, some concepts you're going to have
to get to know on this Dolphins defense.
Number one, a deep disguise rotation
menu on the back end. This defensive
backfield wants to show one thing and
rotate to something else. Number two,
that requires a lot of connectivity.
Smart players in the back end that can
play multiple roles. And number three,
and most importantly across the entire
football field, their physicality. They
are always rerouting at the line of
scrimmage. They want to bring the action
to you and be a physical football team.
Let's go to the tape here and go back to
week one last year against the Detroit
Lions and Jared Goff. And the first
thing you see here is this defensive
presentation. This could be man, this
could be quarters. This could be several
things right here, but it's not going to
be what you get out of the snap because
they're going to rotate into an inverted
two look. And what inverted two means is
you're going to wheel back these corners
into deep half field responsibilities
and your Tampa uh your acting Tampa
linebacker right here is going to be a
safety who just kicks over. So, this
could be quarters with deep quarter
coverage right here, but it's not going
to be that. They rotate the safety in
the middle of the field and they rob
this safety down who is going to
actually make the pick here on this pass
from Jared Goff to Almond Ross St.
Brown. They are playing the sticks. It's
a third down the first down marker right
here at the nine yd line. So they know
they can play everything short and kind
of rally up and make a tackle short of
the sticks. Invert that too and jump
down right here onto this route. This
could be man on St. Brown right here. We
wide into a curl flat responsibility. So
Goff thinks he has this look because
perhaps this safety might be in the deep
half. Maybe he's going to play in the
deep middle but he's not. He's bobbing
down on Alman Ross St. Brown. Goff
thinks he has it, throws it, it's picked
because you confuse the quarterback with
your defensive rotation on the back end.
We jump to another clip in this exact
same game. Once again, we're going to
invert two with a little banjo up top.
Banjo just means we're going to
communicate a possible stack or bunch
here from the lines receivers at the top
of the screen. Here comes the short
motion. And these guys have to decipher
who's going to have first guy in, first
guy out in their banjo coverage. So,
let's go ahead and get to the rotation
because this is also going to be
inverted two, but it presents as
possibly cover one or cover three
because we have a middle of the field
safety. It's not two safeties this time,
one player in the middle of the field
and he's actually going to buzz down
right here and step into the robber
roll. And there go your quarterbacks
once again inverting into deep two. So,
this quarterback deep half right there
and you're going to get another
quarterback that is confused here in
Jared Goff with this presentation who
holds on to the ball for too long and
can't get the ball out and you get a
sack on third down. So that the Packers
defense here once again on third down
knows the sticks. They're not going to
worry about a drag route that kind of
comes open right here or a little flat
to the running back that comes open
because they're trying to set up a play
to get the ball down the field. And you
can tell by Jared Goff's drop right
here. So take a snap from the shotgun.
It's a five-step drop. So he's trying to
push the ball vertically to get the ball
beyond the sticks right here. But the
Packers defense knows that. Jeff Halfley
knows that. So he dials up this inverted
two. Rob this potential crosser at the
sticks. Leave the short routes vacant.
don't cover them because we can rally
and tackle. And the pass rush gets home
as Jared Goff once again can't decipher
this coverage. This is one of the best
quarterbacks in the league at figuring
out what you're doing pre and postnap
and getting the ball off. And the
Packers defense through rotation,
through disguise is confusing him and
getting big production on the back end.
We go to later in the year, another NFC
North opponent here in the Chicago
Bears. Another third down situation.
This is the wild card playoff game.
Third long, you see this the uh the
sticks right there at the 2-yd line.
Caleb Williams wants to throw this ball
into the end zone, possibly to the
sticks to move the chains here, but the
Packers know that and they're going to
play it accordingly. So, once again,
this is going to be a static quarters
look. It's not always going to be about
rotation because if you rotate every
single time, then you kind of lose the
impact of doing that. So, we're showing
quarters here. Deep quarter, deep
quarter, deep quarter. And that's what
it's going to be. What you see is what
you get this time. And they're going to
cut off this little flat route right
here. I think what Caleb wanted was to
work this twoman side right here and
possibly get a little rub route on the
linebacker and free up this running back
for a one-on-one chance to the end zone.
But it's well coached and well covered
there on the flat. Take that away.
Pressure moves him off the spot and the
rotation forces a checkdown. You're
going to get a lot of checkdowns against
this Packers defense for the Miami
Dolphins now with Jeff Hafley because
it's so well coached and connected on
the back end. It forces quarterbacks to
take the easy throw short of the sticks
a lot of the time here in this potential
uh in this third down situation. So they
get off the field once again and this
rotation is going to be the just again
what you see is what you get. Quarters
it becomes quarters after the fact.
Sometimes you show the fast ball, the
get me your fast ball, right? Three 0
count. Just throw a fast ball over the
plate. He's not swinging. And we can get
to that look that way. Now, we're going
to go back to the 2024 season. Jeff
Halfley's first with the Green Bay
Packers when he install a defense that
was really, really good. Top 10 across
the board in most metrics. And you're
going to see a sack here of Matthew
Stafford for the 2024 Rams offense. And
this one's going to be a lot different
in terms of the rotation. So, you're
going to get a middle of the field open
presentation. That just means we have
two split safeties. The middle of the
field is open. And that changes the way
the quarterback approaches the way he
wants to attack the coverage. But you're
going to get rotation where this could
rotate into a possible a robber role.
And then we get maybe cover three. It
could be cover one playing man coverage.
Again, you just don't know what you're
going to get. You do get some man
presentations right here. You're going
to reroute and bump the slot. And this
robber isn't going to wind up being just
a robber. He's going to be in man
coverage. But what he's going to do that
I love so much is we're going to reroute
the fastest player on the field. That's
22 Atwell. He's a 4-2 receiver. Make him
get around physicality. bump him and
help the man coverage you have over 25.
It gets him off of the route and it puts
25 in a great position to get back in
position on man coverage. You're going
to be soft and off on the outside right
here in the zone principles. We're going
to play man or I should say man
principles with a zone principle on the
back end here in your man-free safety.
The reroute down to the flat route.
That's a really good rep there by Evan
Williams. He was a rookie safety in this
Packers defense playing at a high level
in his first year. So, the coverage is
confusing in the postnap rotation, but I
want you to watch the rush right here.
this uh it's going to be a a fiveman
rush. You're going to get a mic twist
blitz right here from the nose backer.
They're going to walk up 56 on the
center and they're going to blitz him
with these four pass rushers also coming
after the quarterback. And what we're
going to do here is we're going to slant
everything hard inside. Both the edges
and the defensive tackles are going to
slant inside. That's going to force this
offensive line to squeeze their
protection. And that gives a linebacker
a chance to loop around for the stunt
and go cut off the escape patch off the
right. A right-handed quarterback wants
to escape to his right. He gets out
there and I'm pretty sure I don't know
for sure, but I'm pretty sure that Quay
Walker had the same conversion rate
here, this offball linebacker, but he
winds up covering the back because he
leaks out into the into the route and
becomes an eligible receiver. If he's
not, if he's in protection, I think Quay
Walker could have twisted off that side
as well as a six-man protection. So, you
can blitz, you can play fourman rush,
and you can do some pressures, too,
which we're going to get here on this
next snap against the Houston Texans,
also in 2024. This is an immediate sack
for Xavier McKenna, who gets a free run
off the edge to CJ Strad. Look at this
presentation. Are they going to bring
rushers? It sure looks like they are.
We're going to play possible cover zero
on the back end. Maybe man coverage
across the board. That is not at all
what you get. Look at the rotation.
They're going to bring four and they're
going to drop seven into coverage after
showing this zero pressure look. And
we're going to get a free run for a
sack. The protection never saw it coming
there as Shout takes that sack. So, what
it winds up being is actually uh Tampa
coverage. Tampa two coverage once again,
which looks like zero, but gets into
Tampa because there goes a linebacker
running the pipe. There's our half field
safeties and we're short here in the
curl flat and cover two and the
protection scheme up front with that
pressure that sim pressure look is going
to get a free run sack on the
quarterback. So whether it's playing
coverage, whether it's rushing the
quarterback, whether it's just rushing
four after the quarterback, the menu is
deep. It requires smart physical players
who can execute multiple roles. And I
cannot wait to watch what Jeff Hafley
puts in place here with this Miami
Dolphins defense.
The first undertaking for Jeff Hafley in
his new job was to round out a coaching
staff and it came together rather
quickly. A mix of backgrounds with
experienced veterans and young coaches
quickly rising through the coaching
ranks. Some of these coaches have
experience with coach Hafley. Some are
retained from the 2025 season. But the
bottom line is this. These are all
teachers first and foremost. Starting
with offensive coordinator Bobby
Slowick. Slowick comes from a family of
coaches. The family business is on the
defensive side of the ball, but Bobby
gravitated towards the offensive side
until he worked with Jeff Hafley in San
Francisco. Half, Bobby, and new Titans
head coach Robert Salah spent a lot of
hours in a dimly lit room cooking up
game plans for some dominant Ners
defenses. And it was that experience
that brought the entire picture together
when Slok returned to the offensive side
of the football. He was the OC and play
caller in Houston for two years,
including CJ Straoud's 2023 Rookie of
the Year campaign. Now, Jeff Hafley also
tabbed Shawn Dugen as his defensive
coordinator. We already covered the
chaotic beauty of the scheme we'll see
deployed here in Miami, and we've heard
from Half on the importance of
relationships. In fact, here's Coach
Dugen on his connection to Jeff Halfley.
>> This will be year
what, eight, eight in a row with him.
So, you know, I think just just building
the defense. Obviously, he has a vision
for what he wants. Kind of taking that
vision and making our defense that. So,
I I think one of the things I love about
working for Jeff is it's not it's kind
of like I was just talking about with
the players. It's not, hey, here's the
playbook. This is what we're going to
do. It's what do we need to do as a
defense to get better and it's always
evolving, right? We're always trying to
to tweak and get better and just put our
best product out there every Saturday or
Sunday.
Coach Hafley hammers home the concept of
doing his duties as the head coach, the
CEO of the football operation, if you
will, and the importance of delegating,
especially with such a trusted cohort in
coach Dugen. Special teams coordinator
Chris Taber has coached three allpromen.
Maybe you've heard of them. Devin
Hester, Josh Cribs, and last year Ray
Davis with the Buffalo Bills. The last
three units he oversaw all ranked top 10
in special teams EPA, the Panthers in 22
and 23, an off year in 24, and then last
year with the Buffalo Bills, a year in
which Buffalo went through three
different punters and three different
place kickers. Six kickers. Talk about
battle tested. Miami also brought back a
pair of beloved coaches from the 2025
staff in Austin Clark who is known in
league circles as one of the best
developers of young talent. He returns
to coach the defensive line while Joe
Barry is back as the run game
coordinator on defense.
We are welcoming in a very special guest
today on this episode of Dolphins HQ.
He's a left tackle of your Miami
Dolphins and on the board of adviserss
for the Dolphins Cancer Challenge,
Patrick Paul. Pat, what's up, man? How
you doing?
>> Hey, doing good. How are you?
>> It's great to see you. How how has the
uh offseason been so far? Body feeling
good? Everything everything feeling
right? Yeah, offseason's been great.
One, I feel amazing as we speak. Just
kind of been doing different things to
keep the body rolling. Yoga, Pilates,
just stuff. Yeah, stuff to keep me
active, loose. So, yeah.
>> Is that new for you? Yoga and Pilates?
>> No, I did it off uh last offseason.
Really just started doing it last
offseason. So, this year just carrying
it over and I I think it helps a lot.
So, yeah.
>> It's It's not just about the flexibility
and stretching, right? Like it actually
makes you stronger. That's what I've
heard, but I'm not really sure. I think
it really correlates a lot to O lineman
because you're in these positions like
this a lot of times. So it's all core.
So Millie like Pilates is all core. So
you're just working the core of your
body and just these slow like slow
tension movements. So I think that
really correlates to O line movement. So
that's why I do it.
>> Makes perfect sense. For a guy that got
sore from playing whiffle ball all day
last weekend, I could probably benefit
from some plies and yoga. Let's get to
what we're talking about here on the
show. What the reason we have you on is
is for the DCC and you're on the board
of adviserss this year and um I just
want to start by getting your kind of
lay of the land for the South Florida
community because you're in year three
here with the Miami Dolphins and this is
a football-rich community but also a
really tight-knit community and the the
dcc is is proof of that. How has your
experience been with getting to kind of
integrate yourself into the South
Florida community?
>> I mean it's been great. Uh the South
Florida community one has been very
welcoming to me. Um this is my home now.
You know uh moved here. this is where
I'm at full-time and where I see myself
being full-time. So, um, honestly, they
welcome you with open arms. The
community is so loving. There's so much
to it and I mean, it's just beautiful,
truthfully.
>> How is it, how how has it differed from
your expectation? Because I think, you
know, rookies get to their new team,
their new city, maybe they have an
expectation going in and it's not the
same as you thought it was going to be.
Has it matched that? Has it been
different? In what ways, if it has been?
>> Oh, that's a great one. Uh, honestly,
your expectations when you get drafted,
you know, I'm from Houston through and
through, so I haven't seen anything else
really. I went to school there, grew up
there, everything. So, you hear stories
by Miami, all nice usually, but uh you
don't know. You never know what it's
truly going to be. And it was, it was
way better than my expectations,
honestly. I mean, it's been great since
I've been here and the people and just
everywhere around here is wonderful.
Truthfully,
>> if you really want to kind of, you know,
get a feel for it, the DCC is a great
place to do it because it's all coming
together for a common cause and it's all
high spirit and really really just a
great time. It's become this this major
major event and the biggest fundraiser
in the National Football League. So, you
have more duties this year, but are you
still riding in the race?
>> Yes, I am. I'm doing the 39 mile ride
this year. So,
>> the Larry Sanka. Let's go. Is that what
you did last year?
>> No, I did the 13 last year. So, this
year I'm bumping it up. Yeah.
>> So, next year maybe the 99.
>> I'm thinking that honestly I'm thinking
that. Yeah.
>> Do Do you use the ebike or is it all
manpower?
>> I'm manpowered now. I'm using the manual
bike and I'm Yeah, I'm getting gritty.
Yeah. I'm doing the whole thing.
>> A lot of guys are going to the ebikes
though. Like my buddy I'm not going to
throw under the bus, but I am
>> do it. OJ McDuffy, former Dolphins
receiver, one of my best friends. He
went ebike recently and he's been
talking about how great that's been on
the knees, but you know, he's got 10
years of playing experience on those
knees.
>> Don't blame him. Don't blame him at all.
But yeah.
>> So, how how do you stay in shape for is
is it different? I mean, the yoga and
plates obviously. Is it the same? Like I
know every sport is different muscle,
right? Is it different training to get
ready for a bike ride?
>> I mean, yeah, strength train regularly.
Um, like today, for example, I did the
bike, so conditioning on the bike,
constantly do that high intervals,
pumping it, pushing it. do like maybe
eight sets of that, 10 on, 10 off, you
know, just getting the conditioning
right. So, just doing that each week,
getting ready for that. But, yeah,
>> I think that'll usually that'll do it
for you, honestly.
>> Blocking Bradley Chub doesn't help you
for a DC event.
>> The mindset, the mindset, you know, you
can carry it over.
>> That's right. So, we talked about this
being your going into your third year
for the Dolphins here. Obviously, this
is your uh your third second DCC because
you got drafted after that. Makes sense.
So, from rookie to board of adviserss is
a pretty big leap. What did you learn
about the event last year that made you
want to pursue more for the DCC?
>> Um, honestly, the first event, you know,
doing the 13-mi ride, I was just a part
of it and it was honestly one of the
best experiences I've had. Uh, it was so
much love that was shown during it and
you're seeing all these different people
who were impacted by it, whether it was
them like themselves or just family
members supporting or just people who
have had, you know, cancer in their
families. So, it was really just it felt
like a just a tight-knit group. everyone
was just so
there was just so much love being shown
and it really affected me in that way
and I just felt like okay I love this
I'm just going to keep on doing it you
know just seeing all the smiles on
people's faces whether what they've been
through just seeing them push through to
all come together to do this it was just
great I've never seen anything like that
before
>> the camaraderies yeah it's it's it's
great is there anything else that you
hope to get out of it I know that's
maybe kind of almost a loaded question
from like a personal standpoint but is
there something you think you can get
out of this more than just you know what
it's been so far
>> just getting to know the people you
know, getting to know everyone who's
doing the ride, who's in my ride this
year for like the 39 milei ride. Just
being able to talk to people and just
hear their story, how they're affected.
I think that's going to be great. So,
yeah, want to keep Yeah.
>> Are there teammates that are involved in
your ride?
>> Uh, yeah, we're going to have a couple
guys doing it. Uh, think Jonah's going
to join in for this one. Maybe Kenneth
Grant. Um, and then, yeah, we're kind of
with the DCC, we're just going to the
players that are doing it, let's spread
them out. So, we have some people doing
the 5K, the 13 mile. Don't know if
anyone's doing the 99 this year. Maybe
one doing the 54. So yeah, everyone's
just going to be spread out.
>> I talked to Jonah earlier this week. I
was like, "You going home this off
season?" Like, "I got to do DCC first."
So he's putting off his trip home. Yes.
>> To do DCC.
>> He's all in. I had to get him all in.
Yeah.
>> You taking credit for that?
>> Oh, that's me.
>> That sounds good. So you you talked
about how, you know, cancer is obviously
a horrible disease that everyone has a
connection to cancer in some way. How
about you? How has cancer impacted you?
>> Uh yeah. Uh when I was growing up, we my
aunt she passed away from cancer. She
came down here, you know, I'm fully
Nigerian. So, she came down from Nigeria
to live with us in Houston to basically
go through her treatments cuz, you know,
Houston has a really big um, you know,
cancer research centers, all that and
the medical center. She came down here
and unfortunately she lost her battle.
So, with that, it's very dear in my
heart. Um, so that's why I initially did
it last year. So this number must make
you feel good then because we're trying
to help that process whether it's
grieving or whether it's you know
treatment whatever it is they're going
to hit $100 million this year. That's
been the goal, you know, for a while now
and that they're going to hit it this
year. What's your reaction to hearing
$100 million raised in cancer research
funds?
>> That's just amazing. I mean absolutely
outstanding. Uh definitely got to get
there and um it's just that's insane.
Honestly, that's my initiate.
>> It's the biggest in the NFL, man. It's
it's a really big deal. How about your
personal fundraising? How has that been
going? And what have you, what have you
done to kind of, you know, get the folks
involved and chipping in?
>> Uh, you know, honestly, just raising
awareness, getting out there and, you
know, making post and whatnot. Um, but
yeah, just got to keep on doing it and
getting more involved and getting people
to, you know, donate in any way they
can, whether it's just showing support,
showing up and actually doing the ride
or just interacting. You could throw a
like, repost, anything. Just anything to
support the cause I think is great.
That's what we have you on the show here
for is to kind of promote that. So, if
you want to tell the folks and you can
address the camera, we've talked about
having a conversation, but you can
address the camera and just tell the
folks where exactly where can they get
involved to help out with this cause.
>> dolphinscancerchallenge.com
and or just any miamiday.com.
Just get involved. Um, interact, join
the ride. I think you have till February
14th to um register for the ride.
Anything. You could do the 5K, you could
do the 13-mi ride, 39 mile, 54 or 99.
all great things. Or just show up and
just be a a supporter, support people on
their routes, anything to just support.
>> That wraps up another episode of
Dolphins HQ from the Baptist Health
Studios right here in Miami Gardens.
Check out my podcast, The Drive Time
Podcast, available three days per week,
wherever you get your podcast from.
Subscribe to the Dolphins YouTube
channel to keep up with the team
throughout the offseason, and we'll see
you here next time.